<u>Profile:</u> an enthusiastic, critical and hardworking behavioural biologist in both, the lab and the field. Interested in endocrinology, animal behaviour and bioacoustics. Passionate about herps and data science in R.

Research interest: behavioural ecology, behavioural endocrinology, data science, bioacoustics.

Expertise: hormones quantification/analysis, sound recording/analysis, behavioural experiments, experimental design, data analysis and visualization, research expeditions, scientific writing.

Languages: fluent in Spanish (mother tongue) and English. Basics in Portuguese.

Education

11/06/2017 — 02/23/2022	PhD. in Biology , doctoral program "Cognition and Communication", thesis "Examining the mechanisms underlying territorial trade-offs in a Neotropical poison frog: behavioural flexibility and sexual hormones" under supervision of Prof. W. Hödl, University of Vienna, Austria.
08/01/2013 - 03/18/2016	M.Sc. in Biology , thesis "Does testosterone correlate with the aposematic syndrome in Amazonian poison frogs?" under supervision of Prof. A. Amézquita, Universidad de los Andes, Colombia.
02/02/2006 – 04/20/2012	B.Ed. in Biology , thesis "Correlación entre el uso de perchas, propagación de cantos y tamaño del territorio en Allobates femoralis y Ameerega trivittata", under supervision of Prof. A. García, Universidad Distrital Francisco José de Caldas, Colombia.

Professional experience

Research experience

April 2022 – Current	Collaborator, "Nutritional tuning of tadpole behaviour", Dr. MT. Fischer & Prof. L. O'Connell, Laboratory of Organismal Biology, Stanford University, USA. Current.
December 2021 – Current	Collaborator, "Contrasting parental roles shape sex differences in poison frog space use but not navigational performance", Dr. A. Pašukonis et al., Laboratory of Organismal Biology, Stanford University, USA. Current.
May 2021 – Current	Collaborator, "Empathy in an early vertebrate, pair bonding poison frogs", Dr. J. Nowicky, BSc. J. Lee & Prof. L. O'Connell, Laboratory of Organismal Biology, Stanford University, USA. Current.
October 2019 – Current	PI, "Testosterone correlates: the role of aromatase in poison frog aggression", Laboratory of Organismal Biology (hosted by Prof. L. O'Connell), Stanford University, USA. 2019-current. Funded by the Company of Biologists.
October 2019 – Current	PI, "Behavioural syndromes of steroid hormones: a non-invasive endocrinological approach to assess animal personalities in poison frogs", Natural reserve 'Les Nouragues', French Guiana, France. 2019-2020. Funded by ÖFFH (Austria) and CNRS (France).
April 2015 – July 2015	Research assistant, Grupo de Ecofisiología, Comportamiento y Herpetología (GECOH). Universidad de los Andes, Colombia.
December 2014 – December 2015	Principal researcher, project "Chitridiomycosis and vocal effort: testosterone immunoredistribution hypothesis in Dendropsophus labialis", Asociación Colombiana de Herpetología, Colombia.
May 2014 – July 2014	Research assistant, Grupo de Ecofisiología, Comportamiento y Herpetología (GECOH). Universidad de los Andes, Colombia.

Teaching experience

January 2019	Statistics Course for PhD's, Department of Cognitive Biology, University of Vienna, Austria.
January -June 2017	Professor-master's degree I, course "Statistical methods", Universidad de la Salle, Colombia.
	Professor-master's degree I, course "Experimental design", Universidad de la Salle, Colombia.
	Professor-master's degree I, course "Descriptive statistics", Universidad de la Salle, Colombia.

August 2013 – **Master's teaching assistant,** laboratory course "*Biopsychology*", Universidad de los Andes, Colombia.

Supervision

January	2020	_	Training/supervision of field assistant B.Sc. L.F. Arcíla-Pérez (Uniquindio, Colombia) in
March 2020			French Guiana: Hormonally mediated social interactions: individual variation and the Challenge
			Hypothesis in Allobates femoralis.

January 2019 – July 2019 – July 2019 – Training/supervision of field & research assistant B.Sc. G. Raboisson in French Guiana and the University of Vienna: Behavioural syndromes of steroid hormones: a non-invasive endocrinological approach to assess animal personalities in poison frogs.

Recent fieldwork

2018 – 2020 **3 Field expeditions** (Approx. 9 months) on behavioural ecology and endocrinology in Neotropical poison frogs, CNRS Nouragues Ecological Research Station, French Guiana.

Consulting

September 2017

May 2021 - current	Data Scientist. Laboratory of Organismal Biology, Stanford University. California, USA.
August 2016 – January 2017	Herpetologist. CORPOAMAZONIA & Universidad Distrital, Colombia.
April 2015 –	Riostatistician, Fundación Guavacanal, Colombia

Grants

2019-2020	PI , Travelling Fellowship by the Company of Biologists: "Testosterone correlates: the roll of aromatase in poison frog aggression.", 2500£ .
2018-2019	PI , Austrian Research Grant for Herpetology (ÖFFH): "Behavioural syndromes of steroid hormones: a non-invasive endocrinological approach to assess animal personalities in poison frogs.", 3440€ .
2018-2019	PI , Nouragues Travel Grant by the French National Center of Scientific Research (CNRS): "Behavioural syndromes of steroid hormones: a non-invasive endocrinological approach to assess animal personalities in poison frogs.", 8340€ .
2014 – 2016	PI , Botas al campo Scholarship by Asociación Colombiana de Herpetología (ACH): "Chitridiomycosis and vocal effort: testosterone immunoredistribution hypothesis in <i>Dendropsophus labialis</i> .", \$2000000 COP .
2014	PI, Seed project - Research Scholarship by Universidad de los Andes: "Effecto de la testosterona en la

territorialidad y desempeño locomotor en dendrobatidos", \$3696000 COP.

2013

PI, Seed project - Research Scholarship by Universidad de los Andes: "Correlación entre el uso de perchas, propagacion de cantos y tamaño del territorio en *Allobates femoralis* y *Ameerega trivittata*", \$3537000 COP.

Communication skills

- Rodríguez, C., Fusani, L., Raboisson, G., Hödl, W., Ringler, E. and Canoine, V. (2020) "Androgen responsiveness to simulated territorial intrusions in *Allobates femoralis* males: evidence supporting the challenge hypothesis in a territorial frog." Video poster, COGSCI 2021 conference, July 26 28, 2021.
- Rodríguez, C., Fusani, L., Raboisson, G., Hödl, W., Ringler, E. and Canoine, V. (2020) "Androgen responsiveness to simulated territorial intrusions in *Allobates femoralis* males: evidence supporting the challenge hypothesis in a territorial frog." Video poster, Virtual Meeting of the Society for Behavioural Endocrinology, June 28 July 2, 2021.
- Rodríguez, C., Amézquita, A., Ringler, M., Pašukonis, A. & Hödl W. "Perch higher and be quieter: acoustic adaptation and sound radiation patterns in *Allobates femoralis*." Oral presentation, Behaviour conference, Chicago, Illinois USA, July 23-27, 2019.
- Rodríguez, C., Amézquita, A., Ringler, M., Pašukonis, A. & Hödl W. "Perch higher and be quieter: acoustic
 adaptation and sound radiation patterns in *Allobates femoralis*." Oral presentation, 20th European Congress of
 Herpetology, Milan Italy, September 2-7, 2019.
- Rodríguez, C. & Beltran, I. "Quitridiomicosis y esfuerzo vocal: Hipótesis de la inmunoredistribución de la testosterona en *Dendropsophus labialis* (Anura: Hylidae)." Oral presentation, I Colombian Congress of Herpetology, Medellin – Colombia, November 20-24, 2016.
- Rodríguez, C. & Amézquita, A. Perch heights, calls and neighbours: "Correlates in *Allobates femoralis* and *Ameerega trivittata* (Anura: Dendrobatidae)." Oral presentation, X Latin-American Congress of Herpetology, Cartagena Colombia, December, 1-5, 2014
- Amézquita, A., Hödl, W., P. Lima, A., **Rodríguez, C.** & Starnberger, I. "The adaptative value of conspicuous coloration in anurans: selection preasures and associated phenotypic traits." Oral presentation at the X Latin-American Congress of Herpetology in Cartagena Colombia.

Publication record

- 1. Pašukonis, A., Serrano-Rojas, S. J., Fischer, M-T., Loretto, M-C., Shaykevich, D. A., Rojas, B., Ringler, M., Roland, A. B., Marcillo-Lara, A., Ringler, E., **Rodríguez, C.,** Coloma, L. A., O'Connell, L.A., "Contrasting parental roles shape sex differences in poison frog space use but not navigational performance" bioRxiv 2022.05.21.492915; doi: https://doi.org/10.1101/2022.05.21.492915
- 2. **Rodríguez, C.,** Fusani, L., Raboisson, G., Hödl, W., Ringler, E. and Canoine, V. (2022) Androgen responsiveness to simulated territorial intrusions in *Allobates femoralis* males: evidence supporting the challenge hypothesis in a territorial frog. *General and Comparative Endocrinology*, 326 114046.
- 3. Bettoni, S., Stoeger, A., **Rodríguez, C.,** and Fitch, W.T. (2021) Airborne vocal communication in adult neotropical otters (*Lontra longicaudis*). *PLOS ONE*, 16: e0251974.
- 4. Chaloupka, S., and **Rodríguez, C.** (2021) Predation by *Leptophis ahaetulla* (Serpentes: Colubridae) on *Osteocephalus cabrerai* (Anura: Hylidae), with a description of its distress call. *Herpetology Notes*, 14: 209-213.
- 5. **Rodríguez**, C., Amézquita, A., Ringler, M., Pašukonis, A. and Hödl, W. (2020) Calling amplitude flexibility and acoustic spacing in the territorial frog *Allobates femoralis*. *Behavioral Ecology and Sociobiology* 74: 76.
- 6. **Rodríguez, C.**, and Hödl, W. (2020). Sound radiation pattern of the advertisement call of the highly territorial poison frog *Allobates femoralis*. *Behavioural processes*, 170: 103996.
- 7. Yeager, J., Zarling, A. and **Rodríguez, C.** (2019) Successful multimodal amphibian defence, handling and recovery costs to would-be predators. *Herpetology Notes*, 12: 279-280.
- 8. Beltrán, I., Ramírez-Castañeda, V., **Rodríguez, C.**, Lasso, E. and Amézquita, A. (2019). Dealing with hot rocky environments: Critical thermal maxima and locomotor performance in *Leptodactylus lithonaetes* (Anura: Leptodactylidae). *Herpetological Journal*, 29: 155-161.

Camilo Rodríguez, PhD.

Curriculum vitae

+(43) 660 2306056 **** camilo.rodriguez@univie.ac.at ⊠

Djerassiplatz 1, 1030, Vienna - Austria 💡

- 9. Amézquita, A., Suárez, G., Palacios-Rodríguez, P., Beltran, I., **Rodríguez**, C., Barrientos, L. S., Daza, J. M. and Mazariegos, L. (2019). A new species of *Pristimantis* (Anura: Craugastoridae) from the cloud forest of the Colombian Northwestern Andes. *Zootaxa*, 3: 537-548.
- 10. Amézquita, A., Ramos, Ó., González, M. C., **Rodríguez, C.**, Medina, I., Simões, P. I. and Lima, A. P. (2017), Conspicuousness, colour resemblance, and toxicity in geographically diverging mimicry: The pan-Amazonian frog *Allobates femoralis*. *Evolution*, 71: 1039–1050.
- 11. **Rodríguez, C.**, and D.M. Pinto. (2013). *Osteocephalus subtilis* Martins and Cardoso, 1987 (Anura: Hylidae): New distribution record. *Check List*, 9 (1): 116-117.

Academic references

Prof. Dr. Walter Hödl

Department of Behavioural and Cognitive Biology University of Vienna Djerassiplatz 1, 1030, Vienna - Austria Email: walter.hoedl@univie.ac.at

Dr. Andrius Pašukonis

CEFE, Univ Montpellier, CNRS, EPHE, IRD, Montpellier, France

Email: andrius.pasukonis@cefe.cnrs.fr